Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- David "Honeyboy" Edwards Series, 1990-1996 and undated, (4 boxes)
  - Birthplace of David "Honeyboy" Edwards. His childhood home, long ago destroyed and plowed under, once stood in this field outside Shaw, Mississippi, 1995 Spring
  - Warehouse District - just south of downtown Memphis, Tennessee, 1995 May
  - Memphis - from atop the train station, looking north/northwest, 1995 May
  - Memphis train station, long closed, 1995 May
  - Painting, downtown Caruthersville, Missouri, 1995 May
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards descending staircase of a bed and breakfast in Derby, England, 1996 Fall
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards backstage in the Wakefield Theatre, Wakefield, England, 1996 Fall
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards with another man. Honeyboy is holding a RC Cola bottle
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards laughing with another man while leaning on the hood of a car
  - Five untitled/undated contact prints of David "Honeyboy" Edwards
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards with family at Alice Edwards' house
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, (7 boxes)
  Images depict the nearly total destruction of Spencer, McCook County, South Dakota by a tornado on May 30, 1998, as well as the following reconstruction of the town, and the tenth anniversary of the tornado. Chatterly is a resident of South Dakota. Original captions taken from back of prints. Prints arranged in original order as received, with some gaps in numbering present.
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints:, (192 items)
    - Jenny Phillips with her cat who was miraculously saved after the tornado, May 1998, 1 (Box 19)
      This is one of the very first photographs I made when I arrived a half a mile north of Spencer on May 31, 1998. People were gethering on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431. A state police barricade would stop many people from entering, including residents. I entered easier than most with my Press Pass. Governor Bill Janklow was there giving the "go ahead" to anybody wanting to board the bus.
    - Entering Spencer by way of Department of Corrections bus the day following the tornado, May 1998, 2
    - Christ figure atop the remains of St. Matthews Lutheran Church in Spencer, May 1998, 3
      F-4 tornado hit the town around 8:30 pm, May 30, 1998.
    - Department of Corrections inmate gathering remains of Evelyn's Antiques the day following the tornado in Spencer, May 1998, 4
    - Apartments (left) where elderly people died in the tornado & across the street from the apartments (right), Spencer, May 1998, 5
      This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Crews removing damaged trees in the aftermath of the F-4, May 30th tornado, Spencer, June 1998, 6
    - Scattered clothing found on the east side of Spencer two days following the tornado, June 1998, 7
    - Men standing where there had been a water tower (left) and rolling down the road headed north on a four-wheeler just outside of Spencer, June 1998, 8
      A kid on a four-wheeler wanted to show Chatterley where a circular saw blade had stuck itself into a tree. This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Newscaster at live broadcast in Spencer, June 1998, 9
    - Kara Arends and Danny Stone looking at a few of their recovered belongings three days after the F-4 tornado. Danny's pickup is upside down on the right side of the image. Both of them were at home at the time with one month old Brandon, their son, June 1998, 10
    - Jenna Webb and Cliff Carlin in the house in Spencer where Jenna's grandmother lived at the time of her passing, June 1998, 11
      Cliff had lived in this house for six months and had considered buying it from the Webbs. The mud on the walls of the house was caused by the water tower falling to the ground during the tornado.
    - Before the big news conference held on June 3, 1998 in Spencer, 12
      Among those present are Governor Bill Janklow, Senator Tom Daschle, Senator Tim Johnson, FEMA Director James Lee Witt, and Vice President Al Gore.
    - Milford Hickman, Division Commander for the Salvation Army, being congradulated by Vice President Al Gore in Spencer, July 1998, 13
    - Boy running in downtown Spencer, July 1998, 14
    - Donated bread and clothing for tornado survivors at the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, July 1998, 15
    - June 4, 1998 - the day nearly 5,000 volunteers came to Spencer to help "comb" the entire town for valuables, clothing, tools, and anything that had not already been picked up, 16
      Governor Bill Janklow asked for 500 volunteers through media outlets just days prior to this event. A F-4 tornado came through Spencer around 8:30 on May 30, 1998, destroying nearly 75% of a town with 325 people. Only six people were killed.
    - June 4, 1998 - the day 5-6 thousand people volunteered to "comb" Spencer, South Dakota for valuables, etc, 17
    - Tables of donated desserts (sandwiches are on other tables) to feed the 5-6 thousand volunteers who showed up to "comb" Spencer on June 4, 1998, 18
    - Lloyd Webb unloading furniture that had been in storage in a friend's barn at the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, January 1999, 111
    - Workers rebuilding the tornado-destroyed bank in Spencer, January 1999, 112
      It was snowing and the windchill was around 25 degrees below zero.
    - Mary Twedt painting trim in the second bathroom at the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota (about 1/2 mile south of Spencer), January 1999, 113
    - Lloyd Webb about to load hay into his pickup in the north pasture not far from the farm house (3 miles north of Spencer) and me in my studio darkroom in downtown Sioux Falls, South Dakota, January 1999, 114
      I rented this studio space from August 1997 to March 2007. This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Mary Twedt in the passenger seat of the Dodge van, with Dave and me on the way to Mitchell, South Dakota to pick up building materials, South Dakota Highway 38, February 1999, 115
    - Danny Stone attaching a canvas to his house in Spencer, February 1999, 116
      Danny is the main canvas sewing employee at Spencer Canvas in Mitchell, South Dakota. He designed and made all the awning for his house.
    - Lloyd Webb and me looking for a lost calf about three miles north of Spencer, February 1999, 117
    - Lloyd Webb putting down a cow that had major problems following the still-birth of a calf the night before, Valentine's Day, 2000, 118
      This was the day (ironically) that we rounded up the last of the cattle on Webb's farm, putting an end to three generations of having cattle on this land. The dead calf was close by and the mother cow was nearly dead at the time of this shooting. It was 15 degrees and windy.
      This print was made from three negatives printed consecutively.
    - Mother cow after Lloyd Webb put her down (hole in skull)., 119
      Her calf is twelve feet away (left). Complications arose the night before while giving birth in the north pasture. Ironically, this was the day Lloyd and I rounded up the remaining cattle for market, leaving the Webb's land free of beef -- only about twenty horses remained. Valentine's Day, February 14, 2000. McCook County, South Dakota.
    - Lloyd Webb (right) and a neighbor herd the very last cows to a trailer to take to market, three miles north of Spencer, Valentine's Day, 2000, 120
      They were among the 25 or 30 that remained on Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farm, thus ending the bovine legacy that began with her father. Nancy refused to help because she was too emotional about this event.
    - The west side of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farmhouse that is part of a new addition, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer, March 1999, 122
    - Lloyd Webb storing a rock-hard (frozen) roll of Linoleum in the barn, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer at the family farm, February 1999, 123
    - Lloyd and Suzy Webb filling the 1950 Chevy with gas in Spencer, March 1999, 124
      Lloyd will buy a 1952 Chevy later in the year. He had a 1953 Chevy heavily damaged in the tornado and regrettably let Bernie Opland crush it and haul it off.
    - Lloyd Webb loading corn to feed the horses while Richard Nixon, the little dog, watches at the barn across from the farmhouse, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, March 1999, 125
    - Tim DeWitt motioning to Steve Tillotson (below, Nancy Webb's brother) while he and Lloyd Webb (hand at right) set roofing joyces on Steve's house in West Spencer, March 1999, 126
    - Danny Stone being interviewed by local television crew in McCook County, South Dakota, March 1999, 127
      This was pertaining to his contractor abandoning the Stone's home construction in Spencer and leaving them $35,000 in debt. A court settlement was finally reached but the Stones filed for bankruptcy a few years later.
    - Dave and Mary Twedt out by the barn pile with their new pet, Sasha, near the intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, March 1999, 128
    - Dave Twedt laying carpet in the living room, about 1/2 mile North of Spencer, April, 1999, 129
      This building had once been the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and it was connected to several motor lodges. Dave bought their home in Spencer around 1990.
    - Mary Twedt with a quilt she made in anticipation of the birth of her first grandchild (Kaitlyn Ann), May, 1999, 130
    - Nancy Stone and Richard Stone planting trees near Danny's house in Spencer, May 1999, 131
      Richard had been living with friends or relatives and coming and ging from Spencer. He is now 17 and thinking of leaving school.
    - Danny Stone (left) and Richard Stone putting up a clothes line not long after celebrating Brandon's 1st birthday, Spencer, May 1999, 132
    - Lloyd Webb setting up two mailboxes in front of the farmhouse on 249th street, McCook County, South Dakota, May 1999, 133
      One box was for him and Nancy and the other was for their daughter Jenna. The mail carrier could not come down this road unless there was more than one mailbox, although Jenna only lived part-time at the farm.
    - Local priests, Catholic officials and altar boys prepare to dedicate the Catholic Parish Center in Spencer on May 30, 1999, 134
      This had been the location of St. Mary's Catholic Church, which was destroyed by the May 30 tornado.
    - Suzy Webb watching Nancy Webb demonstrate standing on one's head one year and one day following the tornado, May 1999, 135
      Bridgette looks on. They are in the north pasture about 1/4 mile from their farmhouse. Nancy's grandfather homesteaded this acreage.
    - Brandon Stone and his father Danny, one year and one day after the Spencer tornado, May 1999, 136
    - Danny and Brandon Stone preparing to pour concrete for the front walk and steps one year and one day after the F-4 tornado took their home, Spencer, May 1999, 137
    - Opening of the Trinity Lutheran Church, Spencer, June 1999, 138
      The church was rebuilt during the years that followed the tornado. The woman in the right image is holding an Argus Leader newsprint, published the day after the May 30 tornado.
    - Richard Stone (right) and his friend Wendy hanging out in front of the Word of Life Church in Mitchell, South Dakota, June 1999, 139
      The youth minister at this church would let kids come and go and Richard was basically a runaway at this time.
    - Danny Stone and Brandon taking a cruise through Spencer shortly after the water tower was completed, July 1999, 140
    - Richard Stone mowing his dad's yard (Danny Stone), Spencer, July 1999, 141
      Richard has returned home after being away for several weeks living on the streets and staying with friends in Mitchell, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt (left) and her daughter, Jessica, out behind the commercial property they are building into a home about a half mile south of Spencer on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, June 1999, 142
      Jessica is nearly 9 months pregnant with her first born Kaitlyn Ann.
    - Mary Twedt in the garden she and Dave planted on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, June 1999, 143
      This is directly in front of the closed motor lodge rooms on the commercial property they are making into a home. Dave is planning to start a herb and vegetable business called "Asphalt Gardens."
    - Tim Dewitt (with hanging sunglasses) and Richard Stone viewing the "Spencer" exhibit at the Washington Pavillion of Arts and Science in Sioux Falls, South Dakota less than one block from my studio darkroom, June 1999, 144
    - Richard Stone watches while Tim Dewitt cut a hole for car speakers in his 1968 Ford Maverick, behind Richard's uncle's house in Spencer, June 1999, 145 (Box 20)
    - Richard Stone and Tim Dewitt on Country Road 431 heading south towards Spencer, McCook County, South Dakota, June 1999, 146
    - Jayson Fredricks holding Kaitlyn Ann the day she was born in Sioux Valley Hospital, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 1999, 147
    - Lloyd Webb and me riding in the north pasture about 1/2 mile from the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer, August 1999, 148
    - Tim Dewitt (standing) and Lloyd Webb about to remove an axle from a truck rear end, near the barn at the Webb's farmhouse, 3 miles north of Spencer, Labor Day Weekend, 1998, 149
    - Isaac Carlin, son of Jenna Webb Carlin and Cliff Carlin, playing on the floor at Lloyd and Nancy's, 3 mies north of Spencer, McCook County, South Dakota, Labor Day Weekend, 1999, 150
      There were several birthdays in the Webb/Tilotson clan celebrated that day (Suzy, Jenna, and Myrta).
    - Tim Dewitt and Richard Stone working late on a Chevrolet Chevette in front of Steve Tillotson's place in West Spencer, South Dakota, late summer 1999, 151
      Steve is Nancy Webb's brother.
    - Tim Dewitt pulling a transmission from an early 1980s Chevy in Steve Tillotson's "junkyard" in West Spencer, October 1999, 152
      Steve is Nancy Webb's brother and the boyfriend of Maggie, Tim's mother.
    - Lloyd Webb in his truck with Nancy's dog Richard Nixon perched on his favorite riding place, at the north pasture on the Webbs' farm, November 1999, 153
      Nixon got his name because he was born in a milkhouse. At first, he was called Milkhouse, which quickly turned to Millhouse, which quickly turned into Richard Nixon. I ran over Richard Nixon when the dog came running out to greet me at Lloyd's birthday party in late March 1999. Lloyd and I took him to the vet in Salem, got him fixed up and returned to the farm to finish the party. They made a pen in the house to keep Richard Nixon from running.
    - Richard Stone out behind the Webbs' barn moving old farm machinery and doing some general clean-up, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, late fall 1999, 154
    - Suzy and Lloyd Webb in the 1952 Chevy heading north on County Road 431, passing an abandoned farmhouse between Spencer and the Webbs' farm, December 1999, 155
    - Lloyd Webb showing Nancy his custom gift-wrapping of a cat-like figure about one week before Christmas, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer in the family farmhouse, December 1999, 156
      The gift was for Myrta, Nancy's sister. Mama cat is in the bottom center.
    - Lloyd, Suzy and Nancy Webb examining the new gun/rifle safe, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1999, 157
    - Suzy Webb with make-up kit at the family farmhouse, McCook County, 3 mies north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1999, 158
    - Richard Stone talking on the phone with a girlfriend, Western Avenue, near 10th street, January 2000, 159
      He is staying part-time with his cousin in Sioux Falls, South Dakota.
    - Richard Stone and his father Danny Stone during a brief visit in Spencer, January 2000, 160
      Richard is currently living with his aunt, Danny's sister, in Baltic, South Dakota.
    - Scattered jigsaw puzzle on the ground following the May 30 F-4 tornado, Spencer, June 1998, 19
    - Workers salvaging grain from destroyed bins, Spencer, June 1998, 20
    - National Guard and Department of Corrections personel working together gathering bags filled by the 5 thousand volunteers the day before, Spencer, June 1998, 21
    - Crews (left) pushing and dumping razed buildings and homes from the tornado aftermath into one of two large pits. Bags (right) of itemes gathered by volunteers the day before that will be cleaned and taken to the McCook Central High School, June 1998, 22
      The hogsed planter belonged to Dave and Mary Twedt. Ironically, this was before I met them. Weeks later, after meeting them, I went with them to McCook Central High School to retrieve items. They gave me the planter and I ended up giving it to my sister, Jolea.
    - Piled up household and domestic toxic material in downtown Spencer, June 1998, 23
      Inmates from the South Dakota Department of Corrections were bussed out there every day to help with the clean-up.
    - Governor Bill Janklow talking to the media in downtown Spencer, June 1998, 24
    - Broken crucifix from the tornado on a table atop the floor of the Trinity Lutheran Church, Spencer, June 1998, 25
    - During the opening prayer at the Trinity Lutheran Church in Spencer, July 1998, 27
      The chruch was destroyed by a tornado on May 30, 1998. This was the last service before a complete razing took place, preparing the way for a new chapel to be built. South Dakota Department of Corrections inmates gather. They had been instrumental in helping clean up efforts from the very beginning a week earlier.
    - Parishoner holding pieces of stained glass window found after the Trinity Lutheran Church was destroyed by the May 30, 1998 tornado, Spencer, after Sunday services had ended on what remained of the church, June 1998, 28
    - Organized volunteers (who stayed for several days) preparing baked beans for workers and volunteers in a tent on Sunday, downtown Spencer, June 1998, 29
    - Orrie Townsend standing on the second story of his house and pointing to the foundation where his house stood the day before the May 30th tornado, June 1998, 30
      He and his wife were not home at the time. Their house was built in the 1980s.
    - Self-portrait in abandoned chair in front of Orrie Townsend's house, Spencer, June 1998, 31
      (Henry operating equipment nearby did not allow me to hear the timer on my camera, thus causing the awkward moment.)
    - Nancy Webb watching the razing of her and Lloyd's house following the May 30, 1998 tornado, Spencer, June 1998, 32
      Nancy was the only person I knew who stood and witnessed their home being razed. I introduced myself shortly after making this image.
    - Volunteers from the Federated Church of God in Des Moines, Iowa placing donated clothing in a drive-away storage bin, in the parking lot of the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, June 1998, 35
      Donated items streamed in for days following the May 30, 1998 tornado. Most of the items were not taken.
    - Downtown Spencer facing south, June 1998, 36 (Box 21)
      The pile of rubble in the distance is one of two such heaps, increasing by the day. Near the end of June, both piles will be set on fire.
    - Abandoned engine, Spencer, June 1999, 37
    - Spencer from the top of the heavily damaged grain elevator that was knocked down and razed weeks later, June 1998, 38
    - Riding with Bernie Opland, heading south on Interstate 29 towards Sioux City, Iowa, just south of Sioux Falls, June 1998, 39
      His truck was loaded with cars he had crushed after the Spencer tornado.
    - Bernie Opland un-chaining cars he crushed in Spencer, June 1998, 40
      Opland and I were leaving the crushed cars at a recycling yard in Sioux City, Iowa. Bernie lived near Baltic, South Dakota.
    - Worker pulling cars off Bernie Opland's flat bed truck at a metal recycling business in Sioux City, Iowa, June 1998, 41
      Bernie crushed these cars in Spencer following the May 30, 1998 tornado. This load was one of several loads.
    - Downtown Spencer through rain on my car window, June 1998, 43
      The dog is fake.
    - Part of the urban planning meeting held for Spencer residents in the McCook County High School gymnasium, June 1998, 45
      The books on the left were being sold by Salvation Army Volunteers. The display board on the right listed all the families and home sites affected by the May 30th tornado. Urban planners from Sioux Falls had suggested that those who rebuild in Spencer try and do so by possibly trading their property and building closer together. Believing that not everybody in Spencer would rebuild, they wanted to avoid large gaps between homes. The idea was roundly rejected by those who planned to stay.
    - Urban planners from Sioux Falls unveiling plans to rebuild Spencer, McCook County High School gymnasium, June 1998, 46
      This was the very last image I made with the original Ilford HP5 from the 100 foot bulk rolls.
    - Hallway at the National Guard Amory, Salem, South Dakota, June 1998, 47
      The six brothers and sisters are in reference to the six deaths during the tornado in Spencer on May 30, 1998.
    - Bernie Opland (who contracted with Spencer to crush cars after the tornado) having a lunch prepared and distributed by the Red Cross, Spencer, June 1998, 48
    - From the back window of my father's 1981 Volkswagen pickup, June 1998, 49
      I would park at the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Rd 431 and work or hitchhike into Spencer during the first 10 days or so following the May 30th tornado. I did not know at the time that Dave and Mary Twedt owned this property, having only met them briefly a few days after the tornado destroyed their home in Spencer. The driver is an unidentified Spencer resident with a truckload of furniture salvaged during the thunderstorm.
    - A small part of the clothing that had been recovered by volunteers in Spencer piled up in the Springfield State Corrections Center near Yankton, South Dakota, June 1998, 50
      Inmates will launder and fold the clothing and it will be offered to Spencer residents in July.
    - Crews digging one of two pits to "bury" Spencer, June 1998, 51
      This was the West pit.
    - One of two massive piles of what was razed in Spencer following the May 30 tornado, June 1998, 52
      The pile was at the southeast edge of town and made from the top of the grain elevator.
      This image was made with a telephoto lens.
    - Volunteers working in the Natinal Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, June 1998, 53
      Donated items streamed in for days following the F-4 tornado that hit Spencer 10 miles west. Most items were not used and they were eventually sent to various organizations like the Slavation Army.
    - Dave and Mary Twedt, Independence Day, 1998, 55
      After having their home in Spencer destroyed by a F-4 tornado, they have decided to rebuild their commercial property into a home 1/2 mile south of town. This was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. Legend has it that an artist traveling through sometime in the 1950s painted the scenic mural on the wall in exchange for several days stay in the adjoining motel. I tried to talk Dave into letting the mural remain in what would become their living room. Consideration was given but the mural fell to the Twedts' hammers the following week. Over the month of July, the Twedts and I filled several dumpster loads in the gutting process of this property.